Guide to the Waldorf School of the Finger Lakes records, 1979-2000.
Waldorf School of the Finger Lakes records, 1979-2000.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Waldorf School of the Finger Lakes records, 1979-2000.
6419
Waldorf School of the Finger Lakes (Ithaca, N.Y.)
13.1 cubic ft.
Minutes, correspondence, records, files, newsletters.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The collection contains minutes of the Board and their correspondence, records of the Care, Development, Coordinating, Finance and Site Committees, information about annual budgets and finance, operational records, personnel and student files, and newsletters.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Waldorf School of the Finger Lakes formally began in the 1982-83 school year. Ann Smith, an experienced Waldorf teacher from England guided the school into existence. The first classes were held in the old West Hill school building. During the second year, the WSOFL moved to a wing of the Community Services Building, and a first grade class was added to the 2-3 and 4-5 classes and kindergarten. In 1984-85 the school moved to more spacious quarters in a public school building in the Danby area. The school added grades over the years. In 1989, the school graduated its first class of eighth grade students and received its charter by New York State.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection contains minutes of the Board and their correspondence, records of the Care, Development, Coordinating, Finance and Site Committees, information about annual budgets and finance, operational records, personnel and student files, and newsletters. It is not a comprehensive collection since record-keeping and maintenance were not always undertaken systematically. Evidence of daily life at the school can be found in the student files, and in folders documenting publicity and promotion, special events and the after school program. Information about the growth and development of the school as well as its eventual financial difficulties and closing will assist researchers charting the history of the school.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Waldorf School of the Finger Lakes (Ithaca, N.Y.); Steiner, Rudolf, 1861-1925.
Subjects:
Alternative schools--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Education--United States.; Education--Experimental methods.; Education, Primary.; Educational sociology.; Elementary school administration.; Waldorf method of education.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Students files, containing detailed narratives about each child attending the WSOFL and personnel files which include applications and contracts are restricted.
CONTAINER LIST
- WSOFL (Waldorf School of the Fingr Lakes) history, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- WSOFL introductory info, 1991-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- About Waldorf education, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Waldorf graduate survey/research, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Waldorf education sources of info., 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Anthroposophical Society: correspondence, brochures, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Anthroposophic/Waldorf literature (from Board Studies, etc.), 1978-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Anthroposophic/Waldorf literature, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Info. from other Waldorf schools, 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Other Waldorf schools - handbooks/newsletters, 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Austin Waldorf School: correspondence, publications, 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Open house/model teaching day, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Calendars of events, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Eurythmy: articles, correspondence, press releases, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Cabin Fever Festival, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Festivals - music and events, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Events/festivals, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- School year calendars, 1984-1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Newspaper clippings: WOSFL and local events, 1983-1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Posters: WSOFL events, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Sketches for newsletters - Justin Kramer (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Photographs: Waldorf students and school, 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Advertisements, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Brochures: promoting WSOFL, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- By-laws/articles of association, 1981-1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Mission statements, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Draft statement of vision and direction, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- School directories, 1981-1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Parent handbooks, 1983-1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- FLRSA (Finger Lakes Rudolph Steiner Association)/Waldorf School Board minutes, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Board Minutes, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Board Minutes, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Board Minutes, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Board Minutes, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Board Minutes, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Board Minutes, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Board Minutes, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Board Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Board Minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Board Minutes, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Board Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Board Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Board Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Board Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Board Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Future Planning - School Closing, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- All School Meeting - School Closing, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- School Closing, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Board Cafe, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Board Development, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Site and capitol development, 1986-1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Site committee minutes, 1992-1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Site - leases prior to 5 Mile Drive, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Site search, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Inlet Valley Trust - 5 Mile Drive, 1987-1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Maps and site for 5 Mile Drive, 1988-1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Tenants - 5 Mile Drive: leases, correspondence, 1990-1998 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Site committee - Oak Hill Manor, zoning/maps/occupancy, 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Site - Oak Hill Manor Correspondence, 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Site committee - 5 Mile Drive addition, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Site committee - 5 Mile Drive land acquisition, 1992-1996 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- New site vision/search, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Vision/goals/long range planning, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Ecovillage, resident request for potential site for school for her children, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Budget (Annual): revisions, statements, accounts, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Budget (Annual): revisions, statements, accounts, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Budget (Annual): revisions, statements, accounts, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Budget (Annual): revisions, statements, accounts, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Budget (Annual): revisions, statements, accounts, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Budget and Financials, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Budget and Financials, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Budget and Financials, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Finance Committee: minutes, handouts, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Budget and Financials, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Finance Committee: minutes, handouts, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Budget and Financials, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Budget and Finance Committee: correspondence, minutes, handout, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Budget: preliminary, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Tuition Aid: applications, forms, worksheets, calculations, 1995-1999 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Meet the board: parents' information night, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Public relations: plans, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Public press announcements, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- P[ublic] S[ervice] A[nnouncement]'s and press releases, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Mailings to public, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Parent participation in the life of a Waldorf school, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Inquiries, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Responses to inquiries, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Misc. letters from before 1990, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence (general), 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to Nursery schools, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Parent correspondence (form letters to parents), 1989-1998 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1982-1999 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous: printed handouts, etc. from WOSFL and other institutions, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Committees (Buisness, Faculty, Executive Committees): minutes, reports, 1984-1999 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Care committe: minutes, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Coordinating committee: minutes, 1993-1999 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Development committee, 1992-1999 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
- Development scenarios, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- [Development]: Annual Giving Ideas, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- [Development]: Annual Giving, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- [Development]: Capitol Campaign Committee, 1993-1999 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- [Development]: Capitol improvement plan, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- [Development]: Donations, 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- [Development]: Fund raising auctions, 1994-1998 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- [Development]: Fund raising committee, 1990-1999 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- [Development]: Fund raising ideas, 1989-1997 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- [Development]: Joan Moora Endowment Fund, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- [Development]: Phonathon, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- [Development]: Phonathon, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Enrollment committee: plans, minutes, correspondence, forms, 1993-1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Telephone survey - enrollment: Enrollment Committee Telephone Survey to boost enrollment, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- College/faculty: faculty of WOSFL and college students, 1980-1998 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
- Parent council: by-laws, minutes, handouts, 1985-1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- After school program: notes handouts, billing, 1989-1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- After school program registration, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Hillside kindergarten registration, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Kindergarten general information, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Pedagogy Committee: minutes, 1989-1998 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- PEP (Parents for Enrichment Programs) tests: mathematics and spelling tests, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Student contracts, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Student contracts, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Student contracts, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Letter of intent, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- [Personnel]: Job descriptions/evaluations, 1986-1998 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- [Personnel]: Resumes for office position, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- [Personnel]: Administrator search, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- [Personnel]: Administrator search, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- [Personnel]: Teacher applications (Box 5, Folder 23)
- [Personnel]: Teacher applications (Box 5, Folder 24)
- [Personnel]: Teacher search/applications (Box 5, Folder 25)
- [Personnel]: Teacher search (Box 5, Folder 26)
- [Personnel]: Teacher search/applications, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- [Personnel]: Employee contracts, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- [Personnel]: Teacher contracts, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- [Personnel]: Teacher contracts, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- [Personnel]: Teacher contracts, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- [Personnel]: Teacher contracts, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- [Personnel]: Teacher contracts, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- [Personnel]: Lists of faculty members, 1982-1994 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- [Personnel]: 3rd grade class, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- [Personnel]: 5th grade class, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- [Personnel], 1990-1996 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- [Personnel], 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 38)
- [Personnel], 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- [Personnel], 1998 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- [Personnel], 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- [Personnel], 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- [Personnel], 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- [Personnel], 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- [Personnel], 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- [Personnel], 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- [Personnel], 1990-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- [Personnel], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- [Personnel], 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- [Personnel], 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- [Personnel], 1998 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- [Personnel], 1997 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- [Personnel], 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- [Personnel], 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- [Personnel], 1994-1998 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- [Personnel], 1990-1997 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- [Personnel], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- [Personnel], 1989 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- [Personnel], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- [Office Records]: AFCU (Alternative Federal Credit Union) debt card, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- [Office Records]: American school directory - online, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- [Office Records]: BEDS (Basic Educational Data Sytem) reports of non-public schools, 1982-1998 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- [Office Records]: Blank forms, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- [Office Records]: Bridge Construction - 5 Mile Drive, 1995-1997 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- [Office Records]: Bulk mailings, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- [Office Records]: Bumper stickers, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- [Office Records]: Information about school buses, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- [Office Records]: CAPE (Council for American Private Education), 1996-1999 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- [Office Records]: Chamber of Commerce, 1990-1996 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- [Office Records]: Cleaning services, 1995-1998 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- [Office Records]: Comprehensive assessment report, 1996-1998 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- [Office Records]: Conference for Administrators of Non-public Schools, 1989-1994 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- [Office Records]: Cornell work study - CIVITAS (Cornell Ithaca Volunteers in Training and Service), 1990-1998 (Box 6, Folder 29)
- [Office Records]: "DANA" (The Development and Administrators Network of AWSNA [Association of Waldorf Schools of North America]), 1995-1998 (Box 6, Folder 30)
- [Office Records]: Fire inspections/drills, 1982-1999 (Box 6, Folder 31)
- [Office Records]: Head lice, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 32)
- [Office Records]: Health/immunization, 1990-1996 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- [Office Records]: Insurance, 1984-1997 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- [Office Records]: Policies and Procedures, 1994-1998 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- [Office Records]: TEACH (Technology Extensions across the Curriculum and Home) early childhood, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- [Office Records]: Telephone services, 1996-1998 (Box 6, Folder 37)
- [Office Records]: Utilities/ground, 1985-1995 (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Newsletters, 1979-1984 (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Newsletters, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 40)
- Newsletters, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 42)
- Newsletters, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Newsletters, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Newsletters, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Newsletters, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Newsletters, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 47)
- Newsletters, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 48)
- Newsletters, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Newsletters, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Newsletters, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Student Files: Abbott - Coleman, D., 1979-1999 (Box 7, Folder 6-64)
- Student Files: Coleman, L. - Gowan, M., 1979-1999 (Box 8, Folder 1-74)
- Student Files: Grant, M. - Kramer, E., 1979-1999 (Box 9, Folder 1-71)
- Student Files: Kramer, J. - O'Brien, E., 1979-1999 (Box 10, Folder 1-74)
- Student Files: O'Brien, H. - Souter-Kline, V., 1979-1999 (Box 11, Folder 1-62)
- Student Files: Speiser, A. - Zisser, Liron, 1979-1999 (Box 12, Folder 1-70)
- Student Applications, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Student Applications, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Student Applications, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Student Applications, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Student Applications, 1994-1995 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Student Applications, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Student Applications, 1996-1997 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Student Applications, 1997-1998 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Student Applications, 1998-1999 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Dept. of Social Services (DSS): correspondence, contracts, certificates of compliance, 1991-1999 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Day Care Regulations, 1985-1999 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Day Care Info., 1988-1998 (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Day Care Misc., 1989-1992 (Box 13, Folder 13)
- DSS Renewal Application, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 14)
- DSS Renewal/Day Care, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 15)
- DSS Renewal/Day Care, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 16)
- DSS Renewal/Day Care, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 17)
- Summer Camp Safety Policies, 1989-1993 (Box 13, Folder 18)
- Summer Camp: brochure, poster, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 19)
- Summer Camp Registration, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 29)
- Summer Camp Staff, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 30)
- Summer Camp Records, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 31)
- Summer Camp Administration, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 32)
- Summer Camp Staff, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 33)
- Summer Camp Records, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 34)
- Summer Camp Staff, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 35)
- Summer Camp, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 36)
- AWSNA (Association of Waldorf Schools of North America) Membership Application, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 37)
- AWSNA Newsletters/Articles, 1990-1998 (Box 13, Folder 38)
- AWSNA Annual Survey Reports, 1993-1999 (Box 13, Folder 39)
- AWSNA Annual School Reports, 1990-1998 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- AWSNA Correspondence, 1992-1998 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Computer documents and programs for fundraising, handbook, donor programs: 5 floppy disks - two 5", three 3-1/4", 1990-1994 (Box 14, Folder 3)